because it's Christmas today we're going
to learn how you can add a snowfall
animation to your website using CSS and
a little bit of JavaScript first what we
are going to do in our HTML is to create
a div with a snowflake class on a
style we're going to style our snowflake
we will make it tiny eight by eight
pixels and we will make it into a circle
with a white background color done we
now have a snowflake to hide the
snowflake we will make it absolute and
we will move it off the screen now we
need to animate our snowflake we want
the flake to go from the top of the
screen all the way down and we also want
to make it disappear for this let's
create an animation called fall we will
start the animation from where our
snowflake is so we will leave from empty
and we will animate our snowflake by
moving it all the way to the end of the
screen and by setting the opacity to
zero then we will add the full animation
we just created to our snowflake set it
to 10 seconds and see how it looks
[Music]
awesome now that we are done with the
animation we can remove the snowflake
from our HTML because the next step is
to use JavaScript to dynamically create
snowflakes and randomize their starting
point before we write any JavaScript we
first have to be comfortable using the
mat that random function the math that
random function will give us a random
number between 0 and 1. a number that
looks like this for example so if we
want a random number between let's say 0
and 10 all we have to do is call Matt
data random and multiply the result by
10. now that we are masters of the math
that random function let's create a
function called make snowflake in our
JavaScript on that function we will
create a div element and we will give it
this no free class so it gets the Styles
and animations we wrote before then we
will call math.random and multiply it by
the width of the screen and we will use
that value to move our snowflake to the
left finally we will get the body of the
document and we will add the snowflake
to it now it's time to call this
function to call it multiple times we
will call it inside of a for Loop that
should run 50 times as you can see it
works we now have 50 snowflakes falling
down because they're all starting at the
same time and that looks weird we need a
random value between 0 and 10 that we
will use to delay the animation now as
you can see they fall at different times
to get a sense of depth we also want to
randomize the opacity we want to make
some snowflakes brighter than others
let's get a value between 0 and 1 which
are also the minimum and maximum values
for the opacity property and give that
to the snowflake we are looking much
better now we want some snowflakes to
fall faster than others for this we have
to change the duration of the animation
so let's delete the animation from our
snowflake on the CSS and back in our
JavaScript we will create a constant of
the minimum duration we want the
animation to be which is 10 seconds and
we will add that constant to another
random value between 0 and 20 which will
be the duration of our animation all
that is left is to set the snowflake
animation with the dynamic duration
value as you can see now some snowflakes
are falling faster than others when the
animation has completed and the
snowflake has disappeared we want to
remove it from the page we don't want to
pollute our HTML full of that snowflakes
for this we will set a timeout using the
set timeout function the set timeout
function allows us to run our code only
after a certain amount of milliseconds
has passed for this we will call set
timeout with the code to remove the
snowflake from the page after the
animation has finished to know when the
animation has finished we can take the
duration plus the delay of the animation
and to turn it into milliseconds we can
just multiply it by 1000 with this tiny
code we can now be sure that the
snowflake will be removed from the page
when it has fallen down and when the
user can't see it if we open our
developer tools we can see the
snowflakes being removed one by one to
make our snowflakes infinite just after
we remove the snowflake from the page we
will call the make snowflake function
again this way when one snowflake dies
another one is created giving us
infinite snow to make everything feel
even more natural in the for Loop that
calls the make snowflake function the
first time 50 times we can use set
timeout again to not create all
snowflakes at once and instead to create
them after a tiny delay and that's it we
are done we now have snowflakes falling
down our page at random speeds opacities
and delays and it looks awesome thank
you for watching this video I wish you a
happy and merry Christmas I hope you are
surrounded by the people you love if you
enjoy the way I explain code and you
would like to learn how to do this sort
of thing to buy yourself then please
click the link below where you will find
an 8 hour free Javascript course where
you will build things like clocks to-do
lists weather with geolocation among
many other things that course is for
absolute beginners and it is free click
the link below and I will see you there
see you on the next one bye
[Music]
foreign